April 15, 1945, southwest of Bergen, Nazi Germany. The British 11th Armored Division liberates
Bergen-Belsen, one of the worst Nazi concentration camps, where he would personify
the true bestiality and horrors of the Nazi regime and its extermination camps.
British forces find 13,000 unburied bodies and nearly 60,000
sick and starving prisoners. Thousands more inmates will die of
diseases such as typhus and tuberculosis during the months following the liberation of the camp.
The British army captures the Nazi men and women responsible for these horrors. Afterwards,
They are forced to help bury the bodies in mass graves. One of them, who would arrive
to be one of the most infamous perpetrators of the criminal Nazi Regime, is Irma Grese.
Irma Grese was born on October 7, 1923 in Wrechen, at that time
part of the Weimar Republic, which ruled Germany from 1918 to 1933.
Irma was the third of five siblings and her parents worked in a dairy.
Adolf Hitler and the Nazi Party came to power in January 1933. The Nazis were
skilled propagandists who used sophisticated advertising techniques,
in addition to the most up-to-date technology of the time, to spread their messages.
The Hitler Youth and the League of German Girls were created as groups
Nazi Party youth. Its goal was to introduce children and young people to the ideology
and Nazi politics. These youth associations also prepared young people
Germans for the war. Irma's father did not sympathize with Nazi ideology. Likewise,
He despised everything related to Nazism, for that reason, he never allowed his children
join Nazi youth organizations, even if they wanted to.
However, it was impossible to avoid the indoctrination of their children,
since schools also played an important role in the dissemination of Nazi ideas
among German youth. From the first days of school, children like Irma Grese were
immersed in the cult of Adolf Hitler. Similarly, his portrait was found in all the
classrooms. While some books were gradually removed from the classrooms, educators
Germans introduced new textbooks, which taught students to love Hitler,
obedience to state authority, militarism, racism and anti-Semitism.
In 1936, when Irma was 13, her mother committed suicide after it was discovered that her husband had a
affair with the daughter of a local pub owner. Her father, Alfred Grese, a devout Christian,
He was very severe and strict with his children, whom he often punished with physical violence.
At school, Irma Grese had poor academic performance. According to Helene,
Her sister, Irma, was bullied at school. As a result, she dropped out of school at the age of
14 years old. After that, he spent six months on a farm doing agricultural work. Later,
He moved to Luchen, where he also worked in a shop for six months.
In 1939, at the age of 15, Grese joined the Hohenlychen sanatorium,
where she worked as a nursing assistant for about two years. At this location,
He trained under the sanatorium's medical supervisor, Karl Gebhardt, a Nazi doctor who,
Later, he would perform medical experiments on the inmates of the concentration camp in
Ravensbrück during World War II. Grese wanted to become a registered nurse.
from the sanatorium, but due to his low academic level, in 1941, at the age of 17,
She was sent to a dairy farm in Fürstenberg, where she operated a butter-making machine.
His criminal career in concentration camps began in July 1942, when he arrived at the
Ravensbrück concentration camp. Ravensbrück, opened in May 1939,
It was the only large women's camp created by the Nazis. In total, some 132,000 women
From all over Europe, people passed through this camp, including Poles, Russians, Jews, and Roma. Of all of them,
More than 92,000 people died in this camp. The Ravensbrück camp staff
It was made up of SS men, who worked as guards and administrators,
and by 150 women who acted as supervisors. These inspectors were volunteers from the SS or
women who had accepted the job because of the good pay and working conditions.
Ravensbrück also housed a training camp for SS guards.
They were trained by Dorothea Binz, a sadistic and cruel Nazi officer and supervisor,
who instructed his apprentices on how to treat the prisoners they were to supervise.
The prisoners' goal was to be worked to death. The task of their supervisors,
like Irma Grese, was to get the most out of them while
were alive. Some 3,500 women were trained at Ravensbrück. After that,
They went on to serve in this center or in other concentration camps.
From the summer of 1942, SS doctors subjected prisoners of war to
Ravensbrück to immoral medical experiments. The main coordinator of these trials was
Karl Gebhardt and his assistants were doctors Herta Oberheuser and Fritz Fischer.
They often used a hammer to break the prisoners' legs. Afterwards,
They infected open wounds with corrosive bacteria and controlled healing.
applying or not applying various chemical substances, such as sulfanilamide, which was one of the first
Antibiotics were used to prevent infections. Similarly, they attempted to help in the treatment
of the amputated soldiers. To do this, they tested various fixation methods and
bone transplants. These experiments included amputations, often performed without anesthesia.
The SS selected almost 80 women, mostly Polish,
for these experiments. Many of them died. Those who survived often
suffered permanent physical damage. Likewise, the SS doctors also
They carried out sterilization experiments on women and children, mostly Roma,
in an attempt to develop an effective sterilization method. Other trials consisted
in performing forced abortions on women who were already seven or eight months pregnant.
In addition to forced abortions, these health workers were also known for beatings.
pregnant women in order to cause spontaneous abortions and kill newborns.
Irma Grese knew Karl Gebhardt from the Hohenlychen Sanatorium. For this reason,
It is believed that in Ravensbrück, Grese, who was 18 years old at the time,
She also worked as a nursing assistant during the conduct of these experiments,
which is why she was exposed to numerous atrocities. This may have influenced
negatively on her personality, turning her into a violent sadist.
When he returned home in 1943 and told his family that he was supervising the
prisoners who worked inside the Ravensbrück compound,
His father beat him with a belt and forbade him from returning home.
In March 1943, Irma Grese was assigned to Auschwitz-Birkenau,
located in German-occupied Poland.
Birkenau was the largest of the more than 40 camps and subcamps that made up the Auschwitz complex.
It was divided into ten sections separated by electrified barbed wire fences.
It was guarded by SS guards, among whom were, from
1942, SS dog handlers. During its three years of operation,
The center had various functions. When construction began in October 1941,
It was supposed to be a camp for 125,000 prisoners of war. However,
It was opened in March 1942 as a branch of Auschwitz dedicated to the extermination of
Jews. In its final phase, from 1944 onwards, it also became a concentration site for
prisoners before being transferred to work in German industry in the Third Reich.
According to Helene, Irma's sister, when she was little, she was afraid to defend herself and always ran away.
to avoid a fight. However, at Auschwitz, Grese was able, for the first time, to hit people.
without them being able to answer him. And he liked it. In time, Grese would become one of
the most hated and feared guards in the camp. Due to her cruelty and brutality, she earned the
infamous nicknames of "the hyena of Auschwitz" and "the beautiful beast". In addition, Grese was reputed to be
a sexual deviant, as she had lovers among the male and female population of Birkenau.
She is also said to have had relations with the infamous doctor Josef Mengele and Josef Kramer,
commander of the Auschwitz-Birkenau concentration camp and later of Bergen-Belsen.
Dr. Gisella Perl, a former Auschwitz inmate, said the following about Irma:
"She was one of the most beautiful women I have ever seen in my life. Her body
was perfect in every line. His face was clear and angelic,
and her blue eyes were the most cheerful and innocent one could imagine. However,
Irma Grese was the most depraved, cruel, and imaginative pervert I have ever encountered."
In her memoirs "Hitler's Ovens", Auschwitz survivor Olga Lengyel,
He reports that Grese had relations not only with Dr. Mengele, but also with
many other Nazis. When it came time to select women for the gas chamber,
Lengyel claimed that Irma Grese deliberately chose the most beautiful prisoners out of jealousy and spite.
Despite everything, Irma Grese had a fondness for some inmates. Such was the case with Nina.
Kaleska, who was 16 at the time, Grese told her that she looked like her sister Helene.
Kaleska was used by Irma as a messenger and as a lookout
when she held lesbian orgies in the barracks. The young woman's mission
was to keep watch so that no one would interrupt them. Grese had numerous romances with prisoners
But when he got bored of them, he selected them to be killed in the gas chamber. He also
beat his sexual partners. On one occasion, when a handsome Georgian
Rejected Grese's advances, he had to watch as Irma dragged his girlfriend by the hair
naked all over the countryside and then whipped her. After torturing the woman he loved,
Grese ordered the man to be shot and the woman sent to the brothel in the countryside.
When Mengele discovered that Grese was sleeping with Jewish inmates, who were considered
racially inferior, he ended his relationship with her. At Auschwitz, Irma fell in love
by Franz Wolfgang Hatzinger, chief engineer of the construction department at Auschwitz I.
Despite this relationship, Grese had so many lovers that, at one point,
He contracted numerous sexually transmitted diseases and, according to Olga Lengyel,
suffered numerous miscarriages. Dr. Gisella Perl performed one of these abortions. After that,
He stated that Irma's only concern was the "pain" she would feel.
Upon arrival at Auschwitz, Grese held various positions within the camp.
At first, Grese was assigned to telephone duties. Later, as punishment,
He was in charge of directing the kommando that transported stones from abroad to the
inside the field. He received this punishment because he wasn't wearing his cap. He was also in charge
of the command that built the roads within the center and the gardening work.
In May 1944, the extermination of Hungarian Jews was to take place.
For 8 weeks, from May 15 to July 9, 1944, officers of the Hungarian Gendarmerie,
Under the direction of the SS, they deported some 424,000 Jews from Hungary to Auschwitz-Birkenau.
Upon arriving at this center, the SS officers selected most of the
them to die in the gas chambers. That same month, at the age of 20,
Grese would become the senior guard at Birkenau's Lager or Camp "C". There,
supervised 6 or 7 female guards who rotated each week. Camp C consisted of 28 blocks
where the prisoners were housed. There was also a dining room, two warehouses with
underwear and clothing and two or three blocks for toilets and sinks.
Normally, this place would only have been suitable for 100 or a maximum of 300 prisoners. However,
The center was so overcrowded that Grese had 1,000 prisoners in each block.
In some of the modules, there were bunk beds large enough for
five people could sleep in. However, most of them had neither beds nor bunk beds.
In Lager C in Grese there were about 30,000 prisoners, all of them Hungarians, while
that the Blockältesten were Czechoslovakians. The Blockältester was the head of the barracks.
Generally, it was a prisoner in charge of ensuring compliance with the rules in
each barrack. He was also responsible for the inmates in the block. As the camp was
overcrowded, the sanitary conditions were horrible. The toilets stopped working
function. Faced with this situation, Grese stated that "wherever one goes,
It's as if the prisoners think that any place is good as a toilet."
In the field, he was infamous for carrying his leather whip wrapped in cellophane.
In this way, human blood could be easily washed away. Normally, it remained on the door.
when the work groups came and went. Then, she would hit the inmates with her whip
simply because he enjoyed doing it. He would later proudly declare:
"It was a very light whip, but if I hit someone with it, it hurt."
Irma Grese beat and mistreated the prisoners to the point that the camp commander,
Josef Kramer ordered him to stop using it. However,
She ignored him and continued using her whip.
The most common reasons for whipping prisoners were theft of food due to hunger.
or the delay in roll call. During these roll calls, which usually lasted from 3:00 a.m.
From morning until 9 o'clock, the prisoners had to remain still. When someone moved,
They beat him or forced him to kneel for hours. Grese's explanation
to attack them was that they were running from one side to the other and she couldn't count them correctly.
Another of his specialties to make these passes as difficult as possible.
The list was to order the prisoners to stand holding,
with each hand, a large stone on their heads. If they hesitated, Grese would immediately hit them.
On one occasion, the inmates cut up their blankets and made them into shoes and jackets.
Grese sternly ordered that all objects made be returned immediately.
with those blankets. However, since nothing was returned, he ordered the blocks to be searched. All those
Female prisoners who had these objects in their possession were brutally flogged.
In addition to her whip, Irma Grese also used to beat inmates with her cane.
Grese's favorite habit was to beat women until they bled and fell to the ground.
After that, he kicked them as hard as he could with his heavy boots.
On one occasion, he saw a woman talking to her daughter over her shoulder.
the wire fence that separated two enclosures. Given this situation,
Grese beat the woman so brutally that the prisoner lay on the ground.
She was also accused of selecting the most veteran inmates for the gas chambers. Often,
She made these selections together with her lover, Dr. Josef Mengele. When the
Women were sent to the gas chamber, Grese noted it in her books as "special treatment."
Survivors later recalled how these captives were often
displayed naked and inspected like cattle. In this way, it was decided whether they were
fit to work in Germany or if they were just fit to die. Grese's function was to maintain the
order and if any woman escaped, he would bring her back to beat her up.
When he saw that relatives were trying to gather in the selection for forced labor,
Irma would beat them until they were unconscious. Then she would leave them on the ground.
The inmates who tried to escape from these selections and were returned, received terrible
beatings that left them bleeding all over their bodies. Afterwards, they were returned to their ranks.
During one of those selections, two girls tried to escape by jumping
out the window. However, they remained lying on the floor. Immediately after,
Grese shot them mercilessly with his pistol, which was always loaded.
Despite everything, Grese also helped some prisoners. This was the case of the inmate
named Alice Tenenbaum, who was 14 at the time. The young woman was sent 16 times to
the gas chamber by Josef Mengele and, on each occasion, Grese saved her by entering
in the gas chamber and carrying Tenenbaum out of it. After the war, Alice
She learned that Grese had saved her so many times because she resembled Helene, Irma's sister.
At Auschwitz, Grese had two huge dogs that she starved.
Survivors remember him cycling around the countryside with the dogs at his side.
side. These accompanied the inmates on their 16-kilometer journey to work.
All those who could not keep up with the pace of the march were attacked by the dogs.
On one occasion, when the female kommando was transporting stones from outside the camp,
The prisoners hesitated and lost control of the cart. It rocked, fell down the hill and
overturned, scattering stones all over the area. A survivor later testified that
It happened: "Irma attacked the two dogs. The girls tried to escape from their fangs,
but the trained killer dogs easily caught up with them. While the animals
They tore the girls' bodies apart, Irma came closer to contemplate the scene. Her eyes were
bloodshot. The sight of the massacre seemed to intoxicate her." All the while
While this massacre lasted, Irma Grese smiled. Sometimes, when Grese went out with her groups
At work, he used to beat women and kick them with his heavy pointed boots.
Another of his specialties was sending women outside the fence.
when they were working. In this way it seemed that they were trying to escape.
When some of the guards refused to shoot the women who had crossed
the fence, claiming that they had been sent deliberately, Grese testified against them.
Thanks to the loot from the victims murdered at Birkenau, Irma was able to choose the most select clothing.
from all over Europe. Grese had her dresses made by the best Jewish dressmakers,
who would become prisoners of the camp. Their favorite garment was a
sky blue jacket with a dark blue tie.
Irma spent hours in front of her dressing room mirror, combing her hair and imagining that
He was a movie star. Grese once declared: "After the war,
I'm going to be in movies. You'll see my name on the screen like a star. I know
life and I've seen a lot of things. I think my experiences will be
useful in my career as an artist." However, I was completely wrong.
Irma Grese left Auschwitz on January 18, 1945, as Soviet forces approached.
to the Auschwitz concentration camp complex and the SS began evacuating
Auschwitz and its subcamps. These forced marches of prisoners from the camps
concentration camps were known as death marches. The prisoners had to walk
long distances under surveillance and in extremely harsh conditions.
Grese participated in one of these forced transports from Auschwitz to Ravensbrück and from
There he went to Bergen-Belsen, where he arrived with a large number of prisoners.
from Ravensbrück in March 1945. Those who collapsed or could not keep up,
were shot by the SS. The prisoners received almost no food even during these marches of the
death and neither when they arrived at the camp. According to the testimonies of the inmates who
were lucky enough to survive the war in Bergen-Belsen, the daily food ration
It consisted of watery soup made with a variety of cooked turnips and 3 and a half centimeters of bread.
day. The sanitary conditions in Bergen-Belsen were terrible. There was no water to wash with and
there was barely enough to drink and cook. These deportations caused the
Bergen-Belsen center was so overcrowded that, during the months of
In winter, when it was freezing cold, prisoners had to sleep sitting on the floor. In addition,
They had to share only 200 blankets in a center that had tens of thousands
of people. Due to the terrible conditions of hunger, thirst and typhus epidemics, the average rate
The daily mortality rate of prisoners was between 250 and 300 dead.
In Bergen-Belsen, Grese continued to mistreat the prisoners who,
In her own words, "they were dirty and sick" even to their bitter end.
Here too he enjoyed hitting and kicking the starving prisoners. Similarly,
He continued to force them to kneel and hold stones over their heads. He often forced them to
standing, from 3:00 a.m. to 9:00 a.m., in the snow, ice, and rain.
Even though people were constantly dying at Bergen-Belsen, Grese not only continued to die
stripping the prisoners and beating them with a rubber baton, but also
subjected women to punishing physical exercises in which they had to parade,
running or doing frog jumps until they collapsed from exhaustion.
About two weeks before the arrival of the British troops, when it seemed that the war
had finished, she was seen hitting a girl with a riding crop. Just before the release,
Grese hit the heads of two sisters when she caught them trying to eat leftovers
of potato peels in the camp kitchen. Although he only worked here for three and a half weeks,
It was so cruel that the inmates nicknamed her "The Beast of Belsen."
On April 17, 1945, 2 days after the liberation of Bergen-Belsen, Irma Grese was
captured by British forces along with fellow Nazi criminal Josef Kramer,
who was the commandant of Auschwitz-Birkenau and
the last of Bergen-Belsen. Grese and other guards of the
SS were temporarily imprisoned in a Wehrmacht training academy,
about three kilometers from Belsen. At that time, she was interviewed by an English journalist.
When he asked her why she had committed all those crimes, Irma replied without shame:
"Our duty was to exterminate antisocial elements to secure Germany's future."
Justice finally reached Grese when she was tried in the Belsen Trials,
which began on September 17, 1945. During the trial, when witnesses
They claimed that she was the worst SS woman in the camp,
Grese replied that everyone was lying, exaggerating, and making an elephant out of a small fly.
Grese only admitted to beatings, but never to killing anyone. However, his lies
They did not help her escape justice. On November 17, the military tribunal
British sentenced Irma Grese to death by hanging. She was 22 years old when the executioner
British Albert Pierrepoint carried out the sentence on December 13, 1945.
His last and only word was "schnell," which means fast in Spanish.
Grese was the youngest woman sentenced to death by British justice in the 20th century.
No tears were shed for Irma Grese.
Thanks for watching World History Channel don't forget to like and subscribe
and click on the notification bell so you don't miss it
our next videos thanks See you next time on the channel